Guide to the International Center for Transitional Justice (ICTJ) Records, 1981-2008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
- Accession (2009-0193), (76 boxes)
  - Institutional Materials (Box 22)
    - War-Affected Children and Youth in Northern Uganda: toward a brighter future, an assessment report, May 2006 (bound)
    - ICTJ publication, Forgotten Voices: a population-based survey on attitudes about peace and justice in Northern Uganda (bound)
    - Ex-combatant Views on the Truth and Reconciliation Commission and the Special Court in Sierra Leone (spiral bound)
    - The Legacy of the Special Court in Sierra Leone (spiral bound)
    - Conference materials: Domestic Prosecutions and Transitional Justice, South Africa, May 16-19, 2005 (2)
    - Presentation, proposal and workshop drafts for ICTJ
    - Article on mass crimes in India
    - Material on East Timor
    - Transitional Justice in Post-Conflict Peacebuilding: an overview of ICTJ activities
    - Miscellaneous correspondence
    - 3-ring binder labeled Democratic republic of Congo (Box 23)
    - 3-ring binder labeled Class lecture materials. Professors A. Boraine and P. van Zyl, Fall 2003
    - 3-ring binder labeled Class materials.
    - 3-ring binder labeled ICTJ Budget, 04/01/03-03/31/04
    - Draft of Repairing the Past: compensation for victims of human rights violations, (4)
    - Conference materials: Trying Heads of State: meeting of prosecution network and pre-publication authors, Sept. 29-30, 2006
    - Materials on East Timor
    - Symposium Proceedings: emerging Intl. criminal justice system & Ad Hoc criminal tribunals
    - Draft of consultancy project proposal for Bosnia & Herzegovina
    - Material on Canada
    - Miscellaneous emails
    - Miscellaneous documents
    - A Review of ICTJ Learning Event Materials, January 16, 2004 (spiral bound) (Box 24)
    - A Workship for the ICTJ, February 5, 2004 (spiral bound)
    - Summary of Personal Interviews of ICTJ Staff and Associates, February 2, 2004 (2 copies, spiral bound)
    - Draft: ICTJ Introduction to Transitional Justice Basic Training Module Presentation Outlines, May 2004 (spiral bound)
    - TRC Trainings
    - GACACA-Internal ICTJ Documents
    - TRC Trainings
    - TRC Trainings - July
    - ICTJ Completion Strategy Collection of Documents (spiral bound)
    - Justice in Transitional Societies: African and Asian Fellows Programs 2003 - Introduction Course Vol II (spiral bound)
    - ICTJ Completion Strategy General Assembly/Security Council Resolutions (spiral bound)
    - Transitional Justice Fellows Programme July-November 2004: Polititcal Transition in Southern Africa (spiral bound)
    - Transitional Justice Fellowship Program 2004 Induction (spiral bound)
    - Justice in Transitional Societies: African and Asian Fellows Program 2003 - Course Reader: DRC (spiral bound)
    - Transitional Justice Fellows Program March-May 2005. The TRC Process in the South Africal Case (spiral bound)
    - Transitional Justice Fellowship Program 2004 Ghana (spiral bound)
    - Transitional Justice Fellowship Program 2004 Rwanda (spiral bound)
    - ICTJ and Centro de Derechos Humanos publication for Universidad de Chile (spiral bound)
    - ICTJ information posters
    - Alliance vs. Network?-ICTJ organizational notes
    - ICTJ Annual Report 2001-2002
    - Teaching Tolerance Program
    - Materials on Afghanistan
    - Materials on Brazil
    - Materials on Ghana
    - Materials on Liberia
    - Materials on Peru
    - Materials on Rwanda
    - Materials on Sierra Leone
    - Materials on Uganda
    - Materials on Transitional Justice Alliance
    - Emails and correspondence to Erik Darko
    - Miscellaneous Articles
    - Miscellaneous emails, outlines, proposals, and notes
    - Photocopies of Annual Report 2003-2004 (Box 25)
    - Material de Lectura spiral bound
    - ICTJ's Project
    - Intelligence oversight-New Zealand
    - Sample Statement-Taking forms
    - Accompanying documents to Eduardo's East Timor trip
    - Analisis de delitos contra los derechos humano y estrategias para su investigacion. spiral bound (2)
    - Miscellaneous materials
    - Emails, memos, & materials-Eric Darko
    - Yellow legal pad with notes on Ghana
    - Miscellaneous emails and drafts
    - Casebook Research Materials compiled by Julie Cordeiro
      - East Timor-Constitution
      - East Timor-Legislation/Regulations
      - East Timor-Cases
      - East Timor-Truth Commission
      - East Timor-UN Reports, regional body reports
      - East Timor-NGO reports
      - East Timor-Press reports
      - East Timor-Academic articles
      - East Timor-Miscellaneous
      - Indonesia-Constitution
      - Indonesia-Cases
      - Indonesia-Statutes and Courts
      - Indonesia-UN reports and regional body reports
      - Indonesia-NGO Reports
      - Indonesia-Press reports
      - Indonesia-Academic articles
      - Amnesty & Pardon-Amnesty: relevant international law
  - Documentation Center materials (Box 26)
    - Fire warden materials
    - Project on Justice in times of transition
    - Carnegie council on ethics and international affairs
    - Materials on corruption
    - Back-up materials contains following folders:
      - Security council retreat report
      - Security council meetings/statements
      - Timor-Leste
      - Haiti
      - DRC
      - Burundi
      - Afghanistan
      - Report on the panel of peace operations
      - Liberia
      - Sierra Leone
      - Kosovo
      - Cambodia
      - Cote D'Ivoire
      - Sudan
    - Guatemala
    - Grenada-TRC
    - Transitional Justice articles
    - Inter-American convention against corruption
    - Miscellaneous academic articles
    - Argentina, Chile, and an article on public apologies
    - Fortunoff Archive for Holocaust Testimonies
    - BALAY
    - The Coexistence Initiative
    - Miscellaneous conference & organization material
    - ICG materials
    - Miscellaneous articles
    - Organizations
    - Materials on children
    - Book: Presidential Inaguration of Father Jenkins, 17th President of University of Notre Dame
    - Miscellaneous articles by ICTJ staff
  - Miscellaneous materials (Box 27)
    - The Final Report of the fact-finding commission. October 1990.
    - Guatemala: memory of silence. Report of the Commission for Historical Clarification Conclusions and Recommendations. (2 copies)
    - Appendices to TRC Report-Sierra Leone
    - Zimbabwe: post presidential election March to May 2002. (spiral bound)
    - A comparative empirical study of retroactive justice decision smade in Zimbabwe and South Africa after independence. (spiral bound)
    - Final Report of the Commission of Inquiry into the involuntary removal or diappearance of persons in the Northern & Rastern provinces. September 191997.
    - RM-Internal files from Doc Ctr Print-outs
    - Internal ICTJ memo: Immunity clause in the SPDC draft Constitution
    - Inputs for the Prosecution Retreat, 9-10 December 2007
    - Gender Task Force Report
    - ICTJ Culture-Princiles & Practices
    - Summary of Personal interview of ICTJ staff and associates. (spiral bound)
    - A workshop fo rhte International Center for Transitional Justice. (spiral bound)
    - Claims Conference Processing report, March 2001 (spiral bound)
    - Folder box labeled: ICTJ Staff Retreat Materials 2006.
    - 3-ring binder labeled: Germany-forced & slave labor.
    - 3-ring binder labeled: Internal Documents: Israel, New Profile - NGO, Critical Perspectives on Military Values, Gender perspectives on militarism, some articles in Hebrew.
    - Darfur. November 2005 (Box 28)
    - Record: newsletter of physicians for human rights. Vol. 19, no. 1, Winter 2006.
    - Darfur: assult on survival. Physicians for human rights. 2006. (2 copies)
    - Public opinion on National Reconciliation in Ghana: survey evidence. 2001 (3 copies) (spiral bound)
    - Democratic policing in West Africa, Workshop Feb. 25-23, 2004.
    - Conference proceedings on national reconciliation and transitional justice processs in West Africa, April 2004.
    - The Military in democratic transitions…the experience of Mali." May 2001.
    - Ghana Center for Democratic Development Annual Report 2001. (2 copies)
    - First annual report of the President of the special court for Sierra Leone. 2002-2003. (2 copies)
    - Special Court for Sierra Leone. March 2003. (2 copies)
    - Second annual report of the President of the special court for Sierra Leone. 2004-2005. (2 copies)
    - Interim report on the special court for Sierra Leone. April 2005.
    - Juridikum. no. 1, 2003 (2 copies)
    - La Chronique. no. 227, October 2005.
    - La Chronique. no. 226, September 2005.
    - Human Rights Forum. Vol. 1, no. 1, January-March 2004.
    - Center for Civic Initiative-Basic Handbook for Human Rights
    - Textes portant creation des commissions de verite. (spiral bound)
    - Etudes sur les commissions de verite. (spiral bound)
    - Commission de droits de l'homme (Nations Unies) (spiral bound)
    - Transparency International Newsletter. December 2001 edition en francais
    - La reconciliation apres un conflict violent: Resume
    - ICTJ op-eds, articles, miscellaneous
    - Srebrenica Materials 09/08: from Louis Bickford
    - NZ-will copy CD
    - Colombia: CNRR Materials from Blaz Guitierrez 05/29/08
    - Sierra Leone materiasl from K. Muddell
    - Special Court of Sierra Leone
    - Cuba Materials - From Eric Darko Files (presum.)
    - Materials from Eric Darko files (presum.)
    - Bogota, Colombia. May 7-9, 2007 Juan Mendez trip
    - ICTJ Press newspaper clippings
    - Fiscalia: General de la nacion
    - Lang. Doc. for Leg. Volume
    - 59th Annual DPI/NGO Conference. 6-8 September 2006.
    - El papel de los parlamentos en america latina para prover la reconciliaion, fortalenciendo asi una sociedad de derecho mas quitativa e inclusiva.
    - Miscellaneous conferences, March 2007
    - ICTJ-Brussels
    - Ghana-National Reconciliation Commission
    - Aequitas Centre de Mediacio Brochure
    - Sierra Leone-TRC
    - Poster-Peru
    - ICC brochure
    - Breaking the silence, building true peace. Zimbabwe
    - CELS: Centro de estudios legales y sociales
    - Veritas Rwanda forum
    - Spiral bound notebook from unknown author found with Sri Lanka documents
    - Miscellaneous materials
    - We want peace, don't we? booklet (3 copies) (Box 29)
    - Posters
    - Courage to refuse
    - Ideele. No. 177, July 2006.
    - Ideele. No. 157, September 2003.
    - Rule-of-law tools for post-conflict states: monitoring legal systems
    - Assistance to justice and the rule of law in Afghanistan, February 2004 report.
    - Project implementation plan progress report. October 2004 (spiral bound) (2 copies)
    - Strategic plan for Timor-Leste Justice Sector. September 2003 (sprial bound)
    - Letter update on War Crimes project in Bosnia & Herezegovina dated 01/24/2005. (2 copies)
    - CSVR Annual Report, 2000.
    - Information and Management Journal. Vol. 37, no. 1, January/February 2003.
    - Fortune. May 13, 2002.
    - Materials on Afghanistan (2 folders)
    - Materials on East Timor
    - Materials on Rwanda
    - Materials on Myanmar
    - Materials on Liberia
    - ICG materials on Sudan
    - Misc. articles w/summaries
    - Order forms for The Pinochet Effect.
    - Materials on Uganda (2 folders)
    - Materials on Sierra Leone (2 folders)
    - Materials from the UN
    - Commentary on the Rome Statue of the ICC (2 folders)
    - Articles on fomer Yugoslav Tribunal
    - Articles on Milosevic
    - Articles on Transitional Justice
    - Large, cloth ICTJ banner from New Delhi conference, 2001 (Box 30)
    - 20 poster size drawings of murder victims
    - Posters for ICTJ's NYU Law course
    - VHS tape labeled Louis Bickford
    - News articles
    - Academic articles (3 folders)
    - Miscellaneous materials
    - Managers of Truch Commissions Affinity Group. 7th meeting, Feb. 21-25, 2005
    - ICTJ agenda for TJ training program Sarajevo, May 5-6, 2008
    - Courage to Refuse Israeli Defense Poster
  - Staff files: Blaz Guiterrez (Box 31)
    Staff Assistant, Americas Program. New York office, 2004-2008.
    - 1 poster
    - 11 CDs labeled Audio for Greensboro
    - 3 CDs from Coordinadora Nacional de Derechos Humanos
    - 4 miscellaneous CDs
    - IDDRS 04.82 (Draft) October 2004
    - Children and Transitional Justice
    - Draft Report on the Ghana National Reconciliation-16 Sept. 2005
    - Caso de la Masacre de Mapiripan vs. Columbia-Amicus Curiae
    - Violacion de los Articulos 7, 5, y 4 en relacion con el articulo 1.1.
    - Constellations of Transitional Justice: Theoretical Perspective by E. Gonzalez-Cueva
    - Cuadernos del Conflicto: Justicia, Verdad y Reparacion en Medio del Conflicto, April 2005
    - Demolishing the Paramilitarie in Columbia: an achievable goal?-5 August 2004
    - Informe de la Comision Interamericana de Drechos Humanos Sobre el Proceso de Desmovilizacion en Colombia
    - ICTJ President's Report to the Board on Activities May-September 2007 (spiral bound)
    - ICTJ Workplan summary, 1 April 2006-31 March 2007 (bound)
    - ICTJ Workplan 2006/07 (spiral bound)
    - Photocopy of Direito a Memoria e a Verdade: Comissao Espacial sobre Mortos e Desaparecido Politicos
    - Crimes contra a humanidade cometidos no Brasil durante o regime militar (1964 a 1985)…
    - Documents on Truth-Seeking
    - Articles on Columbia
    - Panel on ICC-UN, October 18, 2006
    - East Timor-Part 11: Recommendation
    - Narrative Report to The Tinker Foundation, June 2005 - Oct. 2006
    - Article on Reconciliacion en el Peru, by K. Theidon
    - Comision Interamericana de Derechos Humanos
    - Truth and Recociliation Commission (TRC) of Liberia
    - Democratic Republic of Congo-TRC
    - Committee on Organization Issues & ICTJ Retreat (10/19/2004)
    - ICTJ Mission Statement
    - Tax excemption certificate for ICTJ
    - Recomendaciones para Colombia (bound)
    - Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court
    - Articles on Mexico
    - ICTJ on Mexico
    - Propuesta de Reforma Constitucional en Materia de Derechos Humanos… galley proofs
    - Documento de recomendaciones sobre el proyecto de ley estututaria No. 85 de 2003-Senado, demoninado 'de alternatividad penal'
    - Seminario International on Colombia-April 2004
    - European Instrument for Democracy and Human Rights
    - ICTJ on Colombia
    - Article on Eduardo Gonzalez, 2007
    - Indigenous Groups and claims for Reparation: Tentative steps in Peru and Guatamala
    - Human rights and transitional justice
    - Flyers: Desaparicion de Clara Anahi Mariani-1976
    - Pamphlets from Anahi Asociacion
  - Staff files: Ian Martin (Box 32)
    Vice President, New York office, 2002-2005.
    - Draft Peace Agreements: Their Nature and Legal Status
    - Peace Agreements/HR
    - Bougainville Peace Agreement, 30 Aug. 2001
    - The Devil is in the Details: the Challenges of Transitional Justice in Recent African Peace Agreements" by A. Armstrong. October 2004
    - Guidelines for UN Representatives - Conflict Resolution. 14 June 2001
    - OHCHR Darfur Plans
    - Detention
    - Docs related to HR protection in Sudan
    - UNRWA
    - Palestine/Israel Human Rights & transitional justice
    - Palestine-Trusteeship/Intl. Presence
    - Conference Report: How can Human Rights be better integrated into peace processes? (bound)
    - Intervention in Solomon Islands by D. McDougall
    - Prisoner Release and Conflict Resolution: International Lessons for Northern Ireland by K. McEvoy
    - Conciliation Resources Accord Update Issue 8. 2003 (bound)
    - Punishment, Amnesty and Truth: Legal and Political Approaches by T. Hadder
    - Virginia Journal of International Law. Vol. 43, no. 1, Fall 2002
    - Docs related to Peace agreements in Africa
    - Conciliation Resources Accord Issue 13. 2002 (bound)
    - Docs related to Sudan
    - Technical Cooperation Programme-Ethiopia
    - Critical Notes: Special Autonomous Region of East Timor
    - Docs related to Darfur
    - Darfur-Protection
    - Philippines-GRP/NDFP
    - Philippines-Invitation, Schedule
    - Philippines
    - Philippines-Intl. Alert
    - Philippines-Mindanao
    - Philippines-TJ General
    - Philippines-Truth Commission
    - Philippines-Background
    - Philippines-Reparations
    - Monitoring Compliance to International Law: a Tool for Peace-Building in the Israeli-Palestinian Conflict Draft 19 April 2002
  - Mayer-Riecke envelope
  - Staff files: Juan Mendez (Box 33)
    President Emeritus, New York office, 2004-2009.
    - Conference materials: Consultation on the Future of International Justice and Peace and Justice after Conflict, April 2008
    - Conference in Commemoration of the 60th Anniversary of the Genocide Convention, April 4, 2008
    - Conference materials: Genocide: Crimes Unpunished, Lesson Unlearned, April 4-5, 2008
    - Conference materials: Witnessing Genocide: Truth, Reconciliation and the Media, April 6-7, 2008
    - International Seminar on Enforced Disappearances, June 26-27, 2008
    - Memo to ICTJ employees on Health Insurance and Comments by ICTJ on Truth, Justice, and Reconciliation Commission Bill, 2008
    - Brazil articles and newspaper clippings from Eduardo Gonzalez
    - Emails, 2008
    - Registro en Medios ICTJ, May-June 2008
    - Sin Rastro Seminario International sobre Desparacion Forzada
    - Documents on Chad and Sudan
    - Miscellaneous notes
    - Miscellaneous published materials in Spanish, 2008
    - Fujimori: Juicio y Sancion
  - Staff files: Vasuki Nesiah (Box 34)
    Senior Associate in the Gender Program, New York office, 2001-2008.
    - UN University and Princeton University workshop, April 2004
    - Loose pages and folders
    - ICRC Project on the Missing
    - Ghana: TRC Bill
    - Bound drafts from the Truth and Reconciliation Commission
    - South Africa-Amnesty Ch.
    - Liberation of Movements from 1960-1990 (Box 35)
    - 1984 Sikhs' Kristallnacht
    - ICTJ My Documents
    - Other projects
    - Obligations of the African National Congress under International Humanitarian Law
    - South Africa
    - Disappearances
    - Sri Lankan NGOs
    - Current projects
    - Background current info: Sri Lanka
    - HR/Constitutional Background Law
    - Sri Lanka
    - Meetings with external actors (Box 36)
    - Thematic issues
    - Training, internal discussions, and gender consciousness
    - Operational issues
    - TRC case studies
      - East Timor
      - South Africa
      - Sierra Leone
      - Afghanistan
      - Pakistan
      - Liberia gender and TRC
      - Appointments and Liberian contacts
    - Guatemala
    - Haiti
    - East Timor truth commissions
    - TRC and Gender: interviews and research for handbook
    - Thematic issues
    - Operational issues
      - Crimes
      - Rules of evidence
      - Rules of procedure
      - Role of civil society groups, women's groups, victim's groups
      - Role of victims and witnesses
      - Statement taking
    - General
    - Guatemala
    - East Timor
    - Yugoslavia
    - Rwanda and Yugoslavia
    - Background information (Sri Lanka)
    - Emails
    - Fax
    - Letters
    - Gender
    - Background information
    - Amnesties
    - TRC research
    - Truth commissions
    - Unofficial truth projects: summary
    - Truth seeking
    - Community-based truth seeking
    - Twail
    - The Third World and the International Order: Law, Politics and Globalization, 2001
    - Transformation Justice: From Conflict to Resolution and Healing conference
    - Geneva
    - Conferences (2 folders)
    - NGO pamphlets and newsletters
    - Information pieces
    - Historiography (Box 37)
    - Gender and sexuality
    - References and resources
    - International law
    - Human rights
    - Transitional justice
    - Bibliographies
    - Women's issues in Sri Lanka
    - Civilian oversight research correspondence
    - Intelligence reform edit
    - The Missing: The Right to Know documents
    - Unlabelled folders (3 folders)
    - Peruvian Truth and Reconciliation Commission
    - Other articles
    - UN documents
    - Van Boven Guidelines on the right to restitution...
    - International assistance for the rehabilitation and reconstruction of Nicaragua
    - Development and Human Rights: The Role of the World Bank
    - International IDEA
    - International criminal court
    - Human Rights Watch
    - Harvard University Project on Justice
    - Greentree Foundation
    - DePaul University, Internation Human Rights Law Institute
    - Carr Center for Human Rights Policy
    - Legal accountability II (Box 38)
    - Gender and transitional justice in general
    - Unofficial tribunals
    - Reparations work
    - Post conflict development
    - Gender violence in conflict situation
    - Security Council Resolutions 1325
    - Women and peace
    - Defining gender
    - Partner organizations
    - Research resources
    - ICTJ gender program
    - Reparations for slavery
    - Restorative justice
    - Prosecutions
    - Psychology
    - Quotations
    - Racism
    - Reconciliation
    - Reparations
    - Joinet Principles
    - Law and development
    - Memorials
    - Monitor peace and cease agreements
    - Public International Law
    - Local NGOs
    - News
    - Proposals, budgets, and work plans
    - Reparations
    - Role of international actors
    - Truth seeking process
    - Workshops
    - Academic articles: South Africa (Box 39)
    - TRC Legislation, H-Z
    - TRC Final reports
    - TRCs in relation to judges and courts
      - Peru
      - Sierra Leone
      - Chile
      - Theoretical and comparative
    - Comparative lessons, TRC legislation, A-G
      - Chad
      - Chile
      - East Timor
      - El Salvador
      - Germany
      - Guatemala
    - TRCs: General
    - Transitional Justice: General
    - Rule of Law
    - Security and peace
    - Sexuality and human rights
    - Smart sanctions
    - Terrorism
    - Human rights/transitional justice analysis
    - Human rights/transitional justice history
    - International NGOs
    - Justice sector/rule of law
    - Communication
    - Gender
    - Local NGOs
    - News
    - Proposals, budgets, and work plans
    - Reparations
    - Truth-seeking process
    - Workshops
    - Victim groups/victim support and advocacy
    - Fiji
    - Morocco
    - Backgroun information
    - Zimbabwe (Box 40)
    - Meeting materials
    - Zimbabwe binder
    - Indonesia
    - Kenya
    - Rwanda
    - USA
    - Zimbabwe
    - Balkans
    - Burma
    - Colombia
    - East Timor
    - Ethiopia
    - Guatemala
    - Honduras
    - Afghanistan
    - Angola
    - Vasuki Nesiah's Londton and Sri Lanka trip
    - Editorial, books, and journals
    - Dissertation
    - Rule of Law
    - India (Box 41)
    - Equatorial Guinea
    - Colombia
    - DRC
    - Victim support advocacy
    - Universal jurisdiction
    - Academic articles, Ghana
    - Amnesties
    - Background on reparations and restitutions
    - Communication
    - Human rights/transitional justice analysis
    - Justice sector/rule of law
    - Local NGOs
    - Truth seeking process
    - Workshops
    - News
    - Proposals, budgets, and work plans
    - Reparations
    - ICTE conference, 2005
    - Discussion meetings, August 2004 (13 folders) (Box 42)
    - GRP-MILF Formal Peace Talks with OIC Participation, 1993
    - ICTJ Possible approaches to transitional justice in the Philippines, August 2004
    - Geneva guidelines on the electoral rights of conflict forced migrants
    - Disappearances
    - Philippines
    - Ghana (2 folders)
    - Sri Lanka
    - Sri Lanka (TJWG)
    - Principles of Transitional Justice for Demandign Accountability for Disappearances workshop November 2004